Finding Aid for the Music Center records LSC.3261
UCLA Library Special Collections
Music Center records
1732-2018
UCLA Library Special Collections
Music Center of Los Angeles County
LSC.3261
905.4 linear feet (1,609 boxes, 224 flat boxes, 209 shoe boxes, 102 half boxes, 12 phonograph boxes, 8 magazine boxes, 5 map folders, 6 costume boxes, 6 cartons, 4 custom boxes, 3 telescoping boxes, 3 framed prints, 2 oversize flat boxes, 1 oversize carton, 1 negative box, and 1 open reel audio container.)
The Music Center of Los Angeles County, a seven-acre performing arts complex in downtown Los Angeles, opened when the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion raised its curtain for the first time on December 6, 1964. The Ahmanson Theatre and Mark Taper Forum followed in April 1967. The complex expanded to eleven acres on October 24, 2003, when the Walt Disney Concert Hall opened, which includes the Roy and Edna Disney/CalArts Theater and the W.M. Keck Foundation Children's Amphitheatre. The Music Center records range from 1732-2018 and contain the files of the Music Center Operating Company, Otto Rothschild, the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra, the Hollywood Bowl, the Los Angeles Civic Light Opera, the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, the Center Theatre Group, fundraising organizations, the Music Center Education Division, the Walt Disney Concert Hall, and the Music Center Reference Library as well as memorabilia and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL, AUDIO, AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital, audio, and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital, audio, and audiovisual] materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Performing Arts Center of Los Angeles County, 2018.
Custodial History
Mr. Joel Pritkin joined the staff of The Music Center Operating Company on September 8, 1970 as the Archivist for the Music Center. He was responsible for collecting, evaluating, systematizing, preserving, and making available for reference Music Center public records and documents of historical significance. Prior to Pritkin's arrival, Kenn Randall and Norman Macdonald, two of the Music Center's House Managers initiated the archives out of two small storage rooms in the Ahmanson Theatre. Randall and Macdonald undertook to collect historical items from the previous five years of the Center's existence. Because up until that time there was no plan to systematically retain these things, many were lost or scattered throughout the offices and even outside of the Music Center complex. Music Center chief administrator Bill Severns arranged for the purchase of the Raymond F. Barnes collection through the estate. This collection forms a nucleus of reference books and biographies, as well as historical items (mainly programs) covering much of the past of the Music Center and its Resident Groups, along with a wide selection of other theatres around the world. Shortly after Pritkin's hire, the Archives office was relocated to two rooms in the Ahmanson Annex where Pritkin was joined by Archives assistants James Davis and Larry Phillips. Pritkin's role as curator of the Music Center Archives continued until the arrival of Archivist Molly Paradiso circa 1990. Paradiso was joined by Julio Cesar Gonzalez circa 1993. Gonzalez worked as the Music Center Archivist for over two decades until his retirement on September 1, 2017.
Sources: Music Center Operating Company Bulletin, September 8, 1970., Paradiso, Molly. Music Center Operating Company memo, April 12, 1990., Paradiso, Molly, and Julio Gonzalez. Music Center Operating Company memo, July 1, 1993., and The Top O' The Mall IV, no. 1 (January 1971).
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9988093903606533
Biographical / Historical
The Music Center of Los Angeles County, a seven-acre performing arts complex in downtown Los Angeles, opened when the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion raised its curtain for the first time on December 6, 1964. The Ahmanson Theatre and Mark Taper Forum followed in April 1967. The complex expanded to eleven acres on October 24, 2003, when the Walt Disney Concert Hall opened, which includes the Roy and Edna Disney/CalArts Theater and the W.M. Keck Foundation Children's Amphitheatre.
Proposals for a performing arts center in Los Angeles had produced years of unsuccessful discussion and compromise between private citizens, County government, and downtown business organizations. The Music Center's story began with the Southern California Symphony Association's search for a permanent home for the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra.
In 1955, the Board of Supervisors appointed Dorothy Chandler, wife of Los Angeles Times publisher Norman Chandler, as chairperson of a civic committee to promote a performing arts facility for the County of Los Angeles. After many years of negotiation, a County site was designated in downtown's Bunker Hill district with 34.5 million dollars needed for construction. With Dorothy Chandler leading the drive, the Music Center Building Fund of the Southern California Symphony Association was established. Operating out of her home with the help of hundreds of volunteers, 20 million dollars was raised by donations from the business community and private citizens.
A contract between the County and The Music Center Lease Company was then established to build the facility on County-owned property. The remaining balance of 14.5 million dollars was raised by creating a land leaseback arrangement using mortgage revenue bonds.
The Music Center Operating Company (MCOC) was formed in 1961 to oversee the construction and to manage the Music Center complex. The MCOC handled the administration and operation of the Center. Its responsibilities ranged from management of theatre, stage, and box office operations; supervision of a restaurant and concessions; and providing the information center for the complex. The MCOC licensed the use of the three theatres to both long- and short term-tenants. Long-term producing organizations, also known as resident companies, had the first choice of the available time in the theatres. The resident companies included the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra, the Center Theatre Group, the Los Angeles Opera, the Joffrey Ballet, and the Master Chorale.
Source: The Music Center of Los Angeles County History and Description document, Box 402, Folder 11, Music Center records (Collection 3261). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Scope and Contents
The Music Center records range from 1732-2018 and contain the files of the Music Center Operating Company, photographer Otto Rothschild, the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra, the Hollywood Bowl, the Los Angeles Civic Light Opera, the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, the Center Theatre Group, fundraising organizations, the Music Center Education Division, the Walt Disney Concert Hall, and the Music Center Reference Library, as well as memorabilia and ephemera.
The Music Center records also contain the following collections: the Dorothy Chandler collection of awards and memorabilia, the Otto Rothschild photographs collection, the Marion Burke collection, the Edwin Lester Los Angeles Civic Light Opera photographic collection, the Pat Martin Opera collection, the Pilgrimage Play Theatre records, the George Zoritch collection of Playbill Magazine, the Kenn Randall collection of theatre programs, the Charles Coburn collection of sheet music, the Raymond Barnes collection of theatre programs, Mrs. Leiland A. Irish collection of Los Angeles theatre history, and the Olga Rosenthal collection of performing arts ephemera.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series based on the existing order of the records:
Series 1: Music Center Operating Company files, 1949-2017
Series 2: Otto Rothschild files, 1930-2004
Series 3: Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra files, 1909-2010
Series 4: Hollywood Bowl files, 1920-2014
Series 5: Los Angeles Civic Light Opera files, 1935-1998
Series 6: Dorothy Chandler Pavilion files, 1858-2017
Series 7: Center Theatre Group files, 1732-2010
Series 8: Fundraising organization files, 1962-2015
Series 9: Music Center Education Division files, 1970-2014
Series 10: Walt Disney Concert Hall files, 1974-2012
Series 11: Music Center Reference Library, 1872-2018
Series 12: Music Center memorabilia and ephemera, 1919-2018
Separated Materials
The Master Chorale Chief Executive Officer decided to retain their records. All Master Chorale records were transferred to Carol Zamora of the Music Center in 2018 for return to the Master Chorale.
Related Materials
Ernest Belcher papers (Collection 0544). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Eli Broad papers (Collection 2235). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Center Theatre Group records (Collection 0316). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Performing Arts Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Dorothy Chandler papers (Collection 1421). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
East West Players records (Collection 0115). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Performing Arts Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Ernest Fleischmann papers (Collection 2293). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
John Houseman papers (Collection 0816). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Otto Rothschild Photographic Archive (Collection 1381). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Lloyd Wright papers (Collection 1561). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Interview of Ernest Fleischmann [oral history transcript] / Alex Cine, interviewer. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 1999-2000. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Interview of Edwin Lester [oral history transcript] / Betty L. Richardson, interviewer. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 1982. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Interview of Otto Rothschild [oral history transcript] / Jim Stewart, interviewer. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Mark Taper Forum (Los Angeles, Calif.); Ahmanson Theatre (Los Angeles, Calif.); Dorothy Chandler Pavilion (Los Angeles, Calif.); Center Theatre Group of Los Angeles; Walt Disney Concert Hall (Los Angeles, Calif.); Los Angeles Civic Light Opera Association; Rothschild, Otto; Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra; Chandler, Dorothy, 1901-1997; Hollywood Bowl (Los Angeles, Calif.); black-and-white photographs; Music Center of Los Angeles County
- Series 1: Music Center Operating Company files, 1949-2017
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS DIGITAL, AUDIO, AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This series contains both processed and unprocessed digital, audio, and audiovisual materials. Digital, audio, and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  Biographical / Historical
  The Music Center Operating Company (MCOC) was formed July 25, 1961, to manage and operate the facilities known as the Music Center of Los Angeles County on behalf of the County of Los Angeles. Its responsibilities ranged from the management of theatre, stage, and box office operations to supervision of a restaurant and concessions. The MCOC licensed the use of the theatres to both long-term tenants, whose offices are located within the Center, and short-term tenants. The long-term producing organizations were also known as resident companies because they received funding from The Music Center and thus, had first choice of the available time in each of the theatres. In addition to sponsoring the free Symphonian Tours, the MCOC, through its archives, maintained a history of The Music Center from its inception.
  Source: Music Center of L.A. County: Its History and Management document, Box 402, Folder 8, Music Center records (Collection 3261). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
  Scope and Contents
  The Music Center Operating Company (MCOC) files range in date from 1949-2017 and contain Dorothy Chandler's photo albums, outfits, awards and memorabilia; Chandler's assistant Marian Burke's correspondence and transcripts; Music Center Building Fund documents; Music Center Lease Company minutes and correspondence; Performing Arts Council minutes; General Manager correspondence; Board of Directors minutes; booking and lease files; occupancy calendars; Production Department files; financial statements; Operating Committee minutes; Music Center Board of Governors minutes; strategic planning binders; Board of Governors subject files; complex and events files; complex photographs; master calendars; lease events photographs and slides; lease events files; ready reference files; Archives Manager files; Performing Arts Council bulletins; Music Center newsletters; press releases; National State County Partnership grant applications; MCOC-The Music Center merger files; Dedication Week and anniversary materials; Ahmanson Theatre reconfiguration documents; Pavilion and Performing Arts programs; Lease Events programs; The Symphonians President's notebooks; Speaker's Bureau binders; Irene Diener materials; usher uniforms; ephemera; artwork; digital and audiovisual materials.
  - Dorothy Chandler ephemera, 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
    This box contains Hollywood Bowl items including documentation of the Van Cliburn benefit concerts, Dorothy Chandler's personal Bible, Performing Arts Council (PAC) Opportunity Fund correspondence, Pavilion Week Dedication programs, reports, invitations, 1964 December 18 Time Magazine which features Dorothy Buffum Chandler's portrait on the Building the Pavilions of Culture cover, Blue Ribbon Committee invitation, and a guest list for the Founders Reception and Dinner with Richard and Pat Nixon. Folder 10 contains one L.A. Music Center vinyl record composed by Tommy Thompson.
  - Dorothy Chandler Board materials, 1964-2013 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
    This box contains Music Center Operating Company (MCOC), PAC, and MC Unified Fund stationery, a Jacques Lipchitz lithograph record book, a Story Books ledger, clippings, "The Music Center Story" by Nancy Weakly, and Chandler's Board of Governors 1990 campaign book.
  - Dorothy Chandler photographs, 1955-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
    This box contains Los Angeles Times photographs of Dorothy Chandler at Music Center functions such as The Eldorado Party, a party with Pat and Richard Nixon, a signed color photograph of Dorothy Chandler and Zubin Mehta, inscribed by Mehta, contact prints with Princess Margaret, and digital photo documentation. Events and persons included are the opening of the Music Center, Save the Hollywood Bowl, Gregory Peck, the Oscars, the Buck Bag campaign, Frank Sinatra, and the Philharmonic. Folder 11 contains Dorothy Chandler's 132nd Negro Press Anniversary Award. Folder 8 contains six CDs of Dorothy Chandler photographs.
  - Dorothy Chandler ephemera and awards, 1956-2014 (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
    This box contains Blue Ribbon history booklets, programs, and invitations, the Dorothy Buffum Chandler Collection catalogue, clippings, Dorothy Chandler's Music Center Board of Governors meeting binder and reference book, Music Center Opera yearbook, Daughters of the American Revolution Award of Merit, and copies of Dorothy Chandler's obituaries. Folder 11 contains a Chandler Children's Festival 2001 audiocassette. Folder 14 contains one Inventing LA The Chandlers and Their Times DVD.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AND PROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: The audiocassette is not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. The DVD is available for access. All requests to access audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
  - Dorothy Chandler photographs, 1949-1984 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    This box contains photographs of Dorothy Chandler at the Hollywood Bowl, at the Pavilion, and presenting and receiving awards. This box also contains a William Severns Spirit of Los Angeles Award program, a Music Center Memories Otto Rothschild photo scrapbook, Times Mirror Company Resolution of Honor, and a framed recognition for the Performing Arts Council's contribution to the 1984 Olympics.
  - Dorothy Chandler awards and photo albums, 1958-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    This box contains an Award of Distinction from the Governor's Committee for Employment of the Handicapped, a photo album from the editors and photographers of LIFE Magazine, inscribed by David Zeitlin, and a 10th Anniversary Music Center scrapbook.
  - Dorothy Chandler Hollywood Bowl Family Album, 1951-1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    The album was presented to Dorothy Chandler by the Hollywood Bowl Association and includes photographs, correspondence, and artwork by Walt Disney.
  - Dorothy Chandler Founders Album, 1970 August 27 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    The album contains black and white photographs which document the Founders' reception for the President of the United States and includes an invitation addressed to Mr. and Mrs. Norman Chandler.
  - Marian Burke correspondence and programs, 1957-1981 (Box 9, Folder 1-27)
    This box contains correspondence between Marian Burke and Dorothy Chandler, a letter from Spiros G. Ponty to Burke, thank you letter from the White House, copies of the Pavilion, Dedication Week programs, Curtain Call inaugural Ahmanson issue, Peace On Earth dedication invitations signed by Lipchitz, Founders' Reception for the President of the United States invitations and guest list, Lawrence E. Deutsch memorial program, and a Time Magazine inscribed to Marian Burke from Norman Chandler.
  - Marian Burke transcripts and clippings, 1970-2000 (Box 10, Folder 1-12)
    This box contains clippings and magazines collected by Marian Burke, oral history transcripts with Marian Burke and William Severns, and correspondence to Burke from Otis and Bettina Chandler as well as Robert F. Erburu.
  - Marian Burke transcripts and ephemera, 1961-2011 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
    This box contains Marian Burke's revised oral history transcripts, Ojai Visitor's Guide, 100... Remarkable Hollywood Bowl Moments timeline, and her obituary clipping. This box also contains a model of the Music Center on granite for the Grand Patron of the Music Center - Mrs. Norman Chandler and a Town Hall Award presented to Dorothy Buffum Chandler for service to the Southern California Community. Folder 3 contains a Marian Burke oral history audiocassette.
  - Marian Burke magazines and plates, 1964-1993 (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
    The magazines collected by Marian Burke include Time, West, Life, and Los Angeles Times. This box also contains Founders engraving plates which include the invitation for the Jacques Lipchitz Peace on Earth sculpture dedication.
  - Marian Burke Buck Bags, 1955-1965 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
    This box contains three Buck Bags saved by Marian Burke, a related clipping, and Buck Bag Fact Sheets. This box also contains mounted letters of commendation to Dorothy Buffum Chandler from Maurice Mitrani, President Lyndon B. Johnson, and Joseph J. Micciche of the Los Angeles Optimist Club in addition to a laminated Fred Harvey menu.
  - Marian Burke letters and coupons, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 1-5)
    This box contains Buck Bag Campaign letters and coupons for the Music Center Building Fund.
  - Music Center Building Fund statements, 1958-1963 (Box 15, Folder 1-8)
    This box also contains stock donation records and journal entries.
  - Music Center Building Fund contribution reports, 1959-1963 (Box 16, Folder 1-10)
    This box also contains deposit slips.
  - Music Center Building Fund contributions, 1962-1963 (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
  - Music Center Building Fund donations, 1959-1963 (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
    This box also contains paid bills and pledges.
  - Music Center Building Fund contribution slips, 1963-1966 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Music Center Building Fund contribution slips, 1963-1966 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Music Center Building Fund Committee documents, 1955-1965, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 1-10)
    This box contains pledge cards, Welton Becket and Associates Center Theater and Forum study, Welton Becket press release, Cleopatra Premiere Presentation materials, Music Center project estimates, Music Center Progress Reports, and an Organizing for Effective Operations report by McKinsey & Company, Inc.
  - MC Lease Co. construction contracts and reports, 1959-1965 (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
    This box also contains Indenture of Mortgage and Deed of Trust documentation and weekly construction reports from Welton Becket and Associates.
  - MC Lease Co. and Theatre & Forum Lease Co. minutes, 1960-1968 (Box 23, Folder 1-12)
    This box contains Board of Directors meetings minutes, MCOC Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, Analysis Reports, research memorandum, and Academy legal documents.
  - Music Center Operating subleases, 1960-1969 (Box 24, Folder 1-5)
  - MC Lease Co. minutes, 1961-1972 (Box 25, Folder 1-7)
    This box contains Board of Directors meeting minutes.
  - MC Lease Co. construction change orders, 1964-1965 (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
  - Theatre and Forum Lease Co. minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 27, Folder 1-6)
  - Lease correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 28, Folder 1-8)
  - Financial analyses and draft contracts, 1956-1967 (Box 29, Folder 1-9)
    This box contains analyses of the use of operating income and expenses of the Los Angeles Music Center and concession contract drafts.
  - MC Lease Co. Requests for Estimates, 1962-1965 (Box 30, Folder 1-9)
  - MC Lease Co. Requests for Estimates, 1964-1965 (Box 31, Folder 1-3)
  - MC Lease Co. insurance policies, 1962-1965 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - MC Lease Co. correspondence, 1963 March-December (Box 33, Folder 1-7)
    This box contains correspondence files of James Warren Beebe.
  - MC Lease Co. correspondence, 1964 January-September (Box 34, Folder 1-8)
  - MC Lease Co. correspondence, 1964 October-1965 June (Box 35, Folder 1-8)